Ryan Irelan

919-593-5666 ryan@irelan.net ryanirelan.com

Hired, managed, and mentored web developers. I was responsible for building an agency development team that ultimately comprised of 10 individuals of varying experience and backgrounds.

History of leading successful projects for clients from small non-profits up to major brands. My input ranged from focused tactical implementation details to broad, strategic vision for the technical approach for the project.

Scoped and participated in complex projects with multiple client partners where I had limited knowledge and context of the client partners workflows and platforms. The scoping process required establishing relationships with client partners, leading technical discovery, and giving a cost and time estimate that was realistic and profitable.

Professional Experience

Founder/Owner

Mijingo, 2014-Present

My work at Mijingo is split between select consulting work and training product development for web developers and designers. I've been retained to conduct on-site training classes at NASA (Johnson Space Center), Canadian Broadcasting Corporation, State of Texas Office of Court Administration, University of Chicago, and University of Massachusetts Boston.

Vice President, Technology

Happy Cog, 2013-2014

Hiring manager and team leader for entire development team. Responsible for technical decisions for infrastructure, internal projects, and client projects. Assessed, scoped, planned, pitched, and managed projects for brands like Ben & Jerry's and Papa John's.

Technology & Development Director

Happy Cog, 2009-2012

I was the team lead on all web development projects, both internally and for clients. I managed two developers (one front-end, one back-end) on all of our projects. I also interfaced with the clients during sales pitches, project meetings, and during problem-solving situations.

Web Developer

Airbag Industries, 2006-2009

Handled all development tasks—from project kick-off to final deployment—for client web development projects.

Skills

- Employee hiring, training, development, and mentoring
- Technical project scoping and planning
- Explaining technical topics to non-technical stakeholders
- Amazon Web Services, Certified Solutions Architect Associate
- Git version control
- PHP, Laravel, Yii, Codelgniter
- Ruby, Ruby on Rails, Sinatra
- JavaScript
- HTML
- · CSS, LESS, Sass
- Apache
- MySQL
- Content Management System Implementations (custom and off-the-shelf), ExpressionEngine, Craft CMS, WordPress

Selected Publications

Git Essentials, Mijingo, 2017

Craft Essentials, Mijingo, 2017

Up and Running with Flexbox, Mijingo, 2016

Web Performance Testing, Mijingo, 2016

Up and Running with SVG, Mijingo, 2014

ExpressionEngine 2: A Quick-Start Guide, Pragmatic Bookshelf, 2010

The Business Podcast Book, Focal Press, 2008

Education

University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, M.A. in German Studies

Middle Tennessee State University, B.S. in German